the um
so the other question we asked was why
do people not
why they don't see the signs of the Mind
generally why is that something that
needs to be developed first as a student
would say
because the standard they use
for measuring a thing to be a thing
is whether or not you can attend to it
or not but you can't attend to the mind
yeah you um so it's not it cannot be an
object of your attention yeah you can
only discern
the sign or the context of the Mind
see you yeah so why or rather what then
what what
maintains that
standard of expecting or rather
regarding things to exist only if you
can attend to them everything else
Supple than that it's sort of invisible
why is that because people don't choose
to do that they are doing that
I guess there's a view like sign like
the scientific view for example sure
it's a view but what maintains their
View it's not something needs to feed the
it's not something needs to feed the
view being engaged in the senses exactly
a lack of self-restraints exactly so
engaging with the senses for the sake of
pleasure for the sake of avoiding pain
is why people can't see the signs of
their mind even if they learn everything
correctly read the suitors and it says
the prerequisite for the right view is
seeing the signs of your mind they won't
see that unless they have been
sufficiently withdrawn from their senses
um
what else is there necessary say
somebody is withdrawn from their senses
um
what else do they need to do in order to
start even seeing
seclusion so that's another thing you
should say
uh one the one who is not dwelling
secluded that he can see the signs of
the mind that's not possible
so certain physical seclusion is
necessary why is that why is physical seclusion
why is that why is physical seclusion
necessary in order to discern that
background of your experience that where
your mind is why can't you see it when
you're in dwelling with company in
company what's the incompatible aspect there other people
other people
need to be he engages you sort of
kind of pulled out to engage with others
you know there's a kind of cool too but
could you say but you know we are all
observing Noble silence we are all quiet
we're all meditating
watching our breath or whatever nobody's
talking would that be sufficient
there is the possibility of stepping out
basically to engage as he said yeah so
in other words simply perception of
others as others
already prevents that Solitude where you
just with yourself
and yeah so if if a person were to start
from that neutral position as you often
say like and then
learn these things then yeah you could
maybe even in company discern the
background signs of your mind without
these projected views and so on but
nobody starts it in a neutral position
everybody starts already with a Visa
already with ignorance already with
everything else so then you actually
need to withdraw the other way more
until certain things are recognized
such as that background sound of your
mind so where would you be looking for
the signs of your mind practically say
somebody is now sense restrained
guarding of the sense doors
dwelling alone for you know a good part
of the day he's not spending time just
constantly company or with others or
talking to others and so on
where would you start what would you
look for
pressure and intentions
okay
so how would that reveal the mind or
what what would that reveal see spotting
the signs of the Mind chitanimator as a
necessary prerequisite photo like we
where would those signs appear
we can say background sure peripheral
show but more specifically
okay what the students say what is the
mind um um
determined by
what is cheetah determined by perception
and feeling yeah so
so where where do your perception and
feeling meet
just in colloquial terms where would you
find what you perceive and what you feel
nude exactly yeah
so and mood is something see already
something you cannot observe directly
with your eyes ears no it's you can't
feel it tactile with Sensations in your
body yet you are under it it's like the
weather it's like the weather yeah yeah
yeah so that's that's exactly what you
would look for
is there mood
light or heavy
or heavy
elevated or depressed uh lustful or
non-lustful calm or disturbed
constricted or expanded I think all of
these are certain signs are properties
certain limiters
of of already where your mind is
so for somebody who doesn't see this
mind at all or hasn't developed it mood is
at all or hasn't developed it mood is
pretty much what your mind is that's
like if you go in that direction you
will learn more about mine but
as I said as we just said you cannot go
there simply by observing it with your
kind of thoughts or senses because it's
always behind that
you doesn't matter how far back you
travel in your like mentally in your
mind you're always going to remain
within that mood within the reason
outside of it so you're subjected to it
as much as you're subjected to like a
different weather
um and then you just have to do it when
it's present or ignore it if you don't
like it and so on so
so
okay then so say one is then looking in
the direction of the mood
um
what signs and features would they be
discovering on the level of the of that
mood let's say like that
it's risen by itself
is that something you learned or
something you see
um or both no man
it's something you discern in in through
what you're attending to so
um
so you can't attend to the Limit or the
context because otherwise that
that
there will be a context to that that new
thing that you're attending so so what
others then what are the signs would
appear there
on the level of the mood
what are the properties of any mood
doesn't matter if it's good bad elevated
depressed so okay it's there on its own
so okay it's there on its own
I'm subjected to it you're subjected to
it yeah it's painful the fact that it's
but might be very light Pleasant
agreeable can't have enough mood
that is so painful so what change sorry
okay yeah so it's subject to change so
and these are all factual properties
factual limiters often often enduring
mood whatever that mood might be at the
time you're not concerned with the
content of the mood but actually you
want to see what are the characteristics
of any mood good or bad so stay on its
own you are the ones objected to it uh
it can change exactly and and would you
could you even conceive
you preventing a mood from changing or
not or or or or interfering it with it
from the outside that's important any
thought you might have in their
Direction used to within it and that
doesn't change
what's the other
that also sort of determines which
actions are so possible and and seem to
make sense even climbs you in certain
directions you still have Power of
Choice you still have your your manual
your intellect you can use and if it's
you know if a depressed mood is sending
you certain ways you could still use
your reasoning and say no to it the
choice always does remain unto you but
yeah factually it is sloping leaning
sending you in some directions good mood
again sending you towards more of
sensuality more of this more
carelessness more fun or whatever else
bad mood sending you the other way but
the actions that come out of it that's
not on the mood that you accept in that
direction and going with it
why would a person do that
why would a person
uh by default that's what most people do
unless they have learned sufficiently
enough from the suitors and then realize
the value no I must restrain this
why would a person just by default go
with the direction that the mood is
sending them to if I'm angry I would
just be acting angrily if I'm happy I'll
be loving everyone if I'm depressed I
can't get out of bed I'm but I'm acting
out on whatever the mood is whatever
whether I'm just acting further what is
the person that's the way of least
resistance it is what seems to make more
sense against that backgrounds yeah and
what is the so the way of least
resistance that's basically going with the grain
that's basically going with the grain
with the flow with that moves yeah and
that's exactly like what in a video in
Partition about the results with you you
go with the grain that you know the
analog or papilloma and the suit is with
the grain against the grain
so
what is the main product of just going
with the grain of your mood what would
that result in
what's the final result of unchecked
sensuality views cravings
views cravings
ownerships suffering
okay but that's kind of the that's
really the symptom of the problem that
then can make you turn around
what's the chief
that is outside of this no no
sense of self Yeah so basically people
would still see
that they are subjected to their mood
they have no say I mean even a
completely untrained mind would know oh
this bad mood
what is going to end you know this
anxiety for two three days or this this
depression or or even sometimes I get so
excited and I lose control but I would
like to be in control yet they still
identify with that Moon
despite all the signs and features that
are showing you otherwise you still oh
yeah that's me that's what I am that's
who I am because Behavior hasn't been
tracked you've been going with the grain
perpetually and then this view that this
completely different thing that I'm
subjected on there often don't want to
yes that's what I am
so you keep putting yourself first and
there's this blatant kind of indicators
and limiters of the showing you the
things that otherwise you just don't see
them you don't take them rightly and
that's the the simile of the cook we
often mentioned with the unskilled cook
does not see the most obvious signs of
the mind of the king
's preferences and where the king leans
on account of dishes he prepared and
that's why he's then subjected to the
bad moods and ill will and everything
else that that King will punish him with
because personally not knowing these not
spotting these signs then go scalelessly
in these directions and the mind just
proliferates further divided worsens the
suffering increases and there to then
take the the results of that the
Suffering The Pain that's what the Mind
does because you know the Mind suffered you
because you know the Mind suffered you
suffer not because of the world not
because of bad people not because of
suffering in the world you suffer
because your mind is turning against you
on certain occasions my craving is
present that's what suffering is
mind resisting itself aversive towards
itself and that's the pain you feel presence of
and that's the pain you feel presence of
craving means presence of suffering
craving is on the level of that
peripheral background signs of the Mind
so you train the mind you disown it
correctly or you disown yourself in
regard to the mind more accurately
speaking it cannot there's nothing to
turn against
then the highway robbers can be chopping
your limbs off nothing to suffer for
internally there is no English
there isn't fear either
that's the result of all that though
yeah well see and all of that starts by
Discerning the sounds of the mind that
can only be done on the basis of
solitude that can only be done on the
basis of sensor strains seeing the
danger in the slightest fault and
dwelling restrained by the virtue of
precepts keeping the presets yeah and
that's why also perhaps giving the
precepts can experientially seem as
quite dangerous to my identity because
being in a certain mood something might
feel like okay I can do that I make some
determination I'm not going to do this
then the mood changes and then that
previous determination doesn't make much
sense anymore that's where the struggle
begins so then the the the the the the
the guide in principle of your behavior
then is still the mood and your efforts
are secondary to it but if you actually
take the precepts first and say well
regardless of the mood these things will
not be done you have see you still don't
see the mind that wild crazy animal
you're subjected to but actually you're
fancy you don't know where it is specifically
you don't know where it is specifically
but you know it was in this Woodland
last time and you fenced It Off
so you might not see it yet but you know
it cannot be outside of this
because you're not allowing it basically
you're not opening the gates and that's
exactly how then you get closer to start
Discerning these signs because everybody
as I said theoretically can read the
sutta and says oh yeah the two factors
for sorta party and this is where
are you a sort upon it then
because it's not enough to have the
information about what the factors of
the right view is did that make sense of
no factually if that's understood the
Right View needs to be resolved so signs
of the minds are necessarily
prerequisite for for basically becoming
a certified for developing the Right
View and as we explained that's exactly why
and as we explained that's exactly why
because there is an underlying
completely graduated identification with
those moods despite what they're showing
you and you won't be able to see that
for yourself directly up until yeah you
have sufficiently discerned this mind
that endures in the background when
you're in the Solitude and not give in
to Breaking the precepts as a completely
independent thing of you
like completely independent yet you're
fully within it you cannot conceive
existing without it but you were the one
subjected to it
and that's like seeing the nature of
their gratuitous
not the master you know I am second to
this it's that part that people because you
it's that part that people because you
can think
as you said
I have this mood or this bad mood or
that good mood and it's my mood but you
still put yourself as stealing something
as something you can even be yeah yeah
this mind is wild and it needs to
retained an animal and all of that and I
see how it's independent and stuff no no
you see that on the level of information
that intellectual reasoning and as I
said that's true in theory but
practically unless pretty much you are
disowning your actavada
if you are becoming a solo partner
freeing yourself from the Fetters you
are not really seeing what you're saying
you're saying because that has to be the
result if truly discern sounds of the
Mind think correctly the characteristic
of its Anita subject to its will which
is change uh duka basically then there
will be no even most
kind of subtlest abstract Notions of
ownership left there because you truly
you understand the depth of that of this
is an honorable this is not mine and
incidentally that's what escape from it
is
it's not getting rid of it or getting it
under your control it's removing the
senses of traces of ownership and that's
where all the sense restraint and virtue
you understood now you're not doing it
on the level of external Duty you see it
directly relevant
because you realize I can not keep the
precepts and then this crazy wild king
will start stabbing me hitting me
punishing me
I mean I don't need to prove anything to
myself I already saw that this mind
cannot be owned why don't I just protect
this Behavior so it can work peacefully
and I can be you know why would I
torment myself in those ways you would
see a direct relationship between
certain Acts
and mind and certain mental inclinations
such as I'm wholesome acts and the
inclinations of the mind that will then
inevitably have to be felt as suffering
so yeah I'm out of this picture there is
no more antivada involved but factually
mind is still not quite completely free
so if I provide this unsuitable food for
it it will go wild and it will bite me
sure not as bad as before because now I
have tamed it or contained it to degree
but it's still unpleasant
and I have no reason to do it why would
I do it
I mean it's not my problem it's mine my
problem is just so that mine doesn't
torment me and necessarily so then the
whole the the direct kind of
relationship inside recognition between
wholesome is wholesome and why wholesome
is wholesome or rather why because truly
means beneficial
why certain Behavior beneficial and why
it's un beneficial not because the
Buddha said so because literally
beneficial Behavior pains this crazy
mind further it will make King be my
friend who is in the power to touch me or make
who is in the power to touch me or make
my life really miserable unbeneficial
Behavior will send in the other way so I
can choose to go either way but I cannot
unsee this now the direct relationship
between certain type of behavior and how
the mind will incline and where it will
slow and not what it will do
and given that whether putugina or
somebody who practices to azarianship
has the same principle guiding their
behavior which is freedom from suffering
this is really not a choice not much of
a choice
you can get careless maybe and forget
about the king if you if you go
distracted or something but
fundamentally once this is seen a
certain sphere of suffering has been
abolished because you couldn't possibly
intentionally go there anymore
and thus the Mind cannot cause you that
much pain anymore and that's the similar
of the burning charcoal pip like once
you're healed like would you even
consider going and using those burning
embers when you again not that's just
impossible
perhaps you should also clear up the
difference between what we call moods
and what people might think of as
emotion because they're not the same
yeah so that's mood isn't that that kind
of
uh well no you tell me first why don't I
why don't let you speak today what would
the difference be mood and emotion
or what general like again it can mean
different things for different people
but what would emotion mean for people here
I'll be the difference
now it seems to be more particular like
when there is an emotion such as anger
or jealousy or something else that is
still almost something that you can
observe it's not as concrete as material
things you can also have a bit of a
concept in itself but it is
as a background to that and this is what
we're talking about here yeah so the
mood is is yeah it's far more General
broad higher than emotion or any
specific thing so it's that kind of
overall state of mind you're under
person could even say emotion is
somewhat defined by the objects in
regards to which like for example there
is aversion generally but let's say if
it's you know a version in regards to
somebody who has something else that you
would like to have it's like jealousy we
would say or a version regard to
somebody who did something to you that
you didn't like yeah yeah it is more
specific basically it's more content
oriented yeah it evolves around the
content more so
so yeah the mood is then that that
General that the background state of
mind and I guess also yeah it's probably
equally important to say that
um
these characteristics that we discussed
yeah you can obviously hear them hear
them talk recognize read learn about it
and then try to see those things in the
in the mood and sure you have to start
somehow but the point is to start seeing
the mood on its own enduring independent
of your attention
so whether you're attending to your mood
or not you are under it and it can be
for days same mood and you need to start
recognizing that oh there are this
particular specific engagement changes
distractions overall it's still the same
direction my mind leans to
and then start Discerning once you start
seeing it and during on its own dwelling
in solitude obviously not compromising
research then you actually you could
start seeing these features there really
like Discerning from the mood not you
putting it in them in it in the mood
um so so it's important to recognize
that that see that's already a property
of mood that people will not necessarily
see it continues to endure whether you look
it continues to endure whether you look
at it or not whether you try to look at
it or not when you try to attend it and
figure it out you're not you are under
it
three hours later you might try again
it's still the same mood still enduring
all this time
and that's already something that will
be undermining those views of external
and on the point of view for all these
external things happening in succession
in front of me
and so on but practically yeah you gotta
have to restrain which will amplify the
moods increase the pressure increase
that resistance and then see that mood
enduring not giving not spill out not
break the fence around the forest that
you know the mind has to be within
and yeah then you will start seeing its
independence it's a niche all these
things on the level of that Mountain Dew
and all of those stand for signs of the
Mind because when the world says you know
because when the world says you know
it's not they're not specific limit as
you gotta see anything that will stand
for that cheetah for you with the time
and that's then enough to recognize that
that complete uneability of it
yeah oh perhaps we should also clear up that
oh perhaps we should also clear up that
because moods can endure for a while but
at the same time they're in permanent
and that's not a contradiction so they
change and you can find yourself well
that's what impermanence means I mean
subject to change
it remains unchanged but it will have to
change yes that's what an instrument
yeah and that's also then
and that's also then
what you mentioned
recognizing that it endures no matter if
you attend it or not like in the sense
so now I forget about it but then a
couple of hours a new mood no it's not
it's the same mood exactly and that's
then basically right mindfulness it
exactly that's the beginning of it yeah
and then you might find a few hours
later a new mood well it's still a mood
that's what I said you already stopped
looking for the content of your mood
you're looking for the general
characteristic of any mood what is a
Common Thread to any mood so whether you
three you forget about it distract
yourself five hours later there is a
pleasant mood now it doesn't matter it
means oh I'm still under the mood which
means it was unpleasant before it will
change again so
I better not get lost in the content of
that where that mood is directing me
towards yeah and the more one recognizes that
yeah and the more one recognizes that
you can never be outside of a mood the
more that undercuts the Assumption of
self yes because self is the idea that
you can precisely and that's how one
puts oneself outside of it by forgetting
that the mood endures there whether you
think about it or not whether you endure
it when do you attend to it or not yes
and then you forget and then next time
you meet you oh I found this so I've
been outside of this no actually so it's
the way you remember it puts you outside
of it gratuitously or not and write
mindfulness the right memory
that's that's where the practice is
that's where the review starts
description of sotopana in the suitors
is the one who sees skillful is skillful
or good is good and unskillful is
unskillful he sees that for himself no
more Eastern Authority the Buddha the
Sangha other Traditions telling you this
is good he sees for himself good is good
he recognizes it why it is good and as
we described this is why it's good
because it's directly related to the
mind you are the kind of under living
under living under its will under its
own modes are so it's beneficial for my
well-being or unbeneficial for my
well-being either way it's on me to
basically allow it to not
because there's a I see if there's a
relationship between one solitude
a solitude but like kind of having an
attitude of solitude because this good
and bad
um
is really even if you don't think about
it it's always good kind of in the eyes
of somebody or the or the eyes of others
so having that as a as an attitude kind
of thinking of things in relation to
what other people do or what other
people say or what somebody might say or
is just ultimately good because it's
good because hmm
because that in itself can make your
life better or worse hassle or not
but yeah this is on the level of like a
directly relating
to where your mind will incline exactly
so that doesn't require any considerate
it's nothing about anybody else but just
between you and the King nobody else can
come between that yeah and that's that's
the difference as well because then
that's partly I think also why you need
to be withdrawn from from others oh yeah
sure sure because see it is already
harder to see in itself because as I
said you already start with all the
the wrong views and assumptions and not
from a neutral position and then yeah
having the presence of others uh
external kind of your own perceptions
associated with others
selves utters here act as their
ownership everywhere yeah you're not
gonna so it has to be withdrawn then
sure another hand then doesn't mind as
they would have said can sit in any
assembly of the Devils or the Kings his
internal composure doesn't change there
is no introduction of of the old
ignorance is an assumption because that
has been purified beforehand and got rid
of but until that's developed a person
should exactly as the other success
protect his wound so don't eat
unsuitable food don't expose the wound
to the sun because it will get
reinfected cover it up keep it inside away from the
cover it up keep it inside away from the
elements I seclude it done with you know
chasing sense objects and so on uh eat
suitable things don't eat unsuitable
things in other words don't let your
mind go in the unsuitable don't let your
thoughts man I'll go in the unsuitable
directions don't welcome them don't Delight into
don't welcome them don't Delight into
them and the mind will come down and
heal up and then it will be even easier
because again ironically that's that's
why people go further into sensuality
it's because the pain that the Mind
causes but they don't know that the problem the
but they don't know that the problem the
pain is rooted in the mind that's not
free from craving
so that the only escape a person knows
is go back to the pleasure that I don't
the only pleasure I know which is the
pleasure of the senses
but even they go to sincerity because
they want the same thing they want this
mind to not constantly cause them
suffering yes or the need to hear it that they
yes or the need to hear it that they
basically do not have another escape
from they need to well they can hear all
they want they need to stop engaging
with any other form of Escape that they
know that's what we keep saying you have
to give up the management in order to
see where the problem is and then deal
with it there management will mean
avoiding shortcut
yes but if but if this is all together
not pointed out so to speak very
intended by default thing in relation to
suffering will be the sense of pleasure
yeah so somebody needs to present an
alternative to that which engineering
might not make much sense but that needs
to be worked on preferably in seclusion
in order to open up that possibility and
then the dependency on the sensual
blushes will diminish and eventually
disappear yeah it needs to be done
exactly yeah out of Faith you can hear
it you can agree with it you can sound
but unless you start doing it because
you know many people
understand this on the level of
information that you know
that you know
sensuality does not often Escape but
they still engage in management
they still refuse
to fully
feel the weight of the mood that you're
not acting out of towards getting rid of
it
and they will have views they were
justifying and doing it
I don't know if you get rid of your
abandon yeah nobody denies getting a
little independent what we disagree with
is how you go about it
to get into it with a version a version
with a version you reverse towards mind
it's causing you suffering well no
that's exactly why the mind will cause
you to suffer you can't have greed the
version of distraction anywhere else
except on the basis of craving thus you
can't have green diversion distraction
and acting out of it without suffering
you will suffer because of the craving
of it okay now how does someone who does
not see for themselves the distinction
between wholesome and unwholesome know
what is in wholesome and also Mood by
the utterance of another
by learning about it accurately and
knowing where to look for
seeing the background not what they're
directly attending to from their
background the womb of whatever you're particularly
the womb of whatever you're particularly
engage with that's why I was in the list
here to talk about it but I I won't tell
you a whole separate talk to it because
it's a bit too much so you just stick to
the mind that's how they'll see it so
they kind of already see the background
during the while I'm listening to you
talking and generally while I relate to
my senses in my life I'm not thoroughly
completely entirely absorbed in the
objects of my attention yes
um and then if somebody starts talking
about what else is there simultaneously
present while you're attending this
attending that or acting towards this or
acting towards that you get to see that
there is something there truly that this
could pertain to
so out of that faith
you would start doing it and actually
there's a suit that says one without
faith to develop not possible so you
need faith for that
and if the utterance of another is
accurate is properly understood you're not
is properly understood you're not
looking for faults in it you're not
trying to defend your views against it
you're genuinely looking for a medicine
that will cure you from craving thus you
cannot suffer ever you will then take it
on consider it and on the basis of the
of that proper
simultaneous recognition of the
background of your experience not just
directly absorbed into the content and
information and phrasing and so on
it will be enough for you to start at
least to look where is that Woodland
then the mind would where the mind would
hide point is wholesome and Uncle
wholesome is seen correctly why
wholesome is wholesome and unwholesome
is unwholesome
not like there's some some Universal
kind of truth that you discovered
written or this is why wholesome is
always good and so on no you see Ah
that's why wholesome I beneficial is
beneficial and unbeneficial is
unbeneficial and if you have to describe
that then what would it be which one
well why what is wholesome is wholesome
we just did
beneficial is beneficial because it will
keep the mind it will it will not direct
the mind in the direction of increasing
the passion increasing the suffering
increasing the craving it will not
basically disrupt uh anger the king who
will then punish you
that's why it's it's uh it's beneficial
oh it's beneficial to protect this
Behavior because it keeps the king's eye
this crazy mind semi-wild mind that I
still you know
can't trust
keeps him keeps him content keeps him
calm keeps him happy keeps him
predictable thus keeps me safe
beneficial as it happens those things
are things that are not rooted in greed
aversion delusion so loving kindness is
beneficial is good generosity is beneficial it's
is good generosity is beneficial it's
good not acting out of anger is
beneficial and it's good
but this is primarily why it's
beneficial not because other people will
like you and account of it no because
the mind will not punish you on account
of it that's why it is good so it
happens that the whole world the whole
world and society would also benefit
from the same thing but although the
secondary reasons consequently the
unbeneficial akusala things are things
that would aggravate the Mind further
that would infest the wound further the
one that they would have pulled the
arrow out but you still need to keep an
eye on her until it heals so the mind
can still turn
you know kick and scream if you keep
subjecting it to distraction sensuality
acting out of your will and you are
careless but if you're not it will come
down and generally you have to regard it as
and generally you have to regard it as
something that well you cannot be
identified with you are under and
any suffering from the smallest you can
imagine to the greatest possible
language you can think of
will be caused by nothing other than
that mind still being capable of craving
against itself not by losing everything
there in the world and so on that is
literally nothing to do with the pain
it's the craving of the Mind means
presence of pain no craving no pain the
Noble Truth like oh
this is the root of suffering in the
entire Cosmos in all of the ends of
existence in the entire samsa nothing
else presence of craving or absence of
presence of craving or absence of
craving so you could now even take the
principle further and say beneficial
things are the ones that do not increase
the craving and prevent the future
craving from arising and unbeneficial
ones are the ones that do the opposite
so for your own welfare for your own
good man seeking his own welfare his own
good as I said to say you would
recognize because as I said even wild
unrestrained person still wants the same
thing do not suffer
on that level fundamental level that
he's subjected to
so if he comes to recognize the true
reason for suffering he cannot not heed
it
and that's the whole point of the Four
Noble Truth you can't reverse that
because it actually undermined all of
the previous it was the reason like
craving was the reason for all of your
previous actions and attempted escape
and management and so on and now you
found it and now you see a direct
connection between what contributes to
Woods craving and what kind of makes it
diminish uh without making things worse
and that's all to it really that's why
it says you know even out of hand who is
free completely from any possibility of
that mind
reappearing in the form of craving ever
again he still continues dwelling
secluded guarding of the sense doors
because that's that's truly Pleasant
abiding Here and Now
it's actually truly agreeable to not
engage with the senses to not engage
with the burning embers and now he's
removed any reason to do so so he'll
continue not doing so because the reason
for doing so was that very craving that
you're trying to get rid of by making it
worse the the the lack of the infected skin
the the the lack of the infected skin
you're reaching you're ripping it
scratching gets you relief but increases
the scratching increases the itch
when when the Buddha talks about
crushing the mind or the mind
it's often interpreted I think in a way
where the order is yeah in order to
crush the mind with the mind you need to
see what the mind is it says questioning
the context with the context of that
well yeah yeah it's crashing that that
background mode by not giving in to the
whatever it leans to but
yeah it's it's something you need to see
in building first
and again how can you practice
you know the people like to
what do people believe they die you know
leads to the right view you can do it
before you have the right view you can
practice mindfulness the full Foundation
of mindfulness when one is like knowing
like all these like basically ways the
mind will be enduring there and
Discerning it accurately without
interfering with it without trying to
change it but again he knows depressed
mind is depressed man related mind and
late he knows mind of blast is mind of
effectively lust or not affected so
already thoroughly versed in recognizing
that while the elephant all the data
that you trapped and then seeing it how
it endures in different mood and all of
that keeps hammering in
the the common thread of the Mind the
common characteristics that's the whole
point it's not oh he he knows the
depressed man is depressed minds and
then he does this and this and this and
this and this to abandon the depressed
mind no knowing it is enough because you
as we said in beginning it's not about
the content
so it's not whether your mind is
depressed or related or this or that the
fact is that mind that you are subjected
to that cannot be owned the trigger
trude is to keep identifying yourself
with oh you want to keep hammering in those
oh you want to keep hammering in those
characteristics they will prevent you to
keep identifying with
Anita duka then anata is the result
cannot be utter anymore
in that regard taming and disowning
is
yeah yeah
what do you think
so how does taming
can you let's put it like this Can you
tame your mind without disowning it or
rather can you dishonest without taming
it
no because you will be unable to endure
the pressure that it exerts over here
but can you tame it without disowning it
can you do that
I guess
it comes together in the sense well it
depends maybe what you mean by taming
like you could it means basically sort
of uh not
typing it so it doesn't really turn
towards craving as much doesn't really
attack you as much it's actually calmer
like even listens to what what Mana what
food Mano presents itself you might make
it presents to it sorry you can make a
start taming the might well there is
still some sense of ownership exactly
yeah so you can't take your mind without
necessarily Banning ownership but
obviously abandoning the ownership boy
will be much easier that mine is already
attained um and then with the mind is what Satya
um and then with the mind is what Satya
samadh is so I want to practice Amanda
you want to practice concentration
inverted commas yeah God sends those
dwelling Solitude and observe the signs
and features of the background moves
that you are subjected to that is the
definition of samadhi and composure
not ignore those things by focusing on
one point in this nostril tip or
something like that that's quite the
opposite that's literally ignoring
the behavior of the king and just
focusing on the fork or his hand or his
foot or this or that so you don't see
the unpleasant truth that that's
overwhelming you now or he's about to
punch you he's about to throw you in
jail but as long as I focus on this one
point I won't be aware of the bars
around me
and that's not an escape
like it it does provide some relief but
it requires constant maintenance
basically and that's yeah in the same
sense as we said scratching scratching
the infected Age provides effect for
relief but it's making much worse see
you are making this worse you're
ignoring the Kings
hints and preferences
um so it's going to be even more annoyed
with you so next time he won't just put
you in jail he's going to give you 100
whips as well
because this is the hundredth time
you're doing the same stupid thing yeah
that's what sensuality versions
that's with preferences in chasing
sensuality in that sense or aversion
what makes things worse makes your mind
even Wilder even more bitter even
sharper pain even people they've been
acting out of anger their whole life you
know and they reach certain age you just
and they reach certain age you just
perpetually depictive and angry even
when there's no reason anymore
because yeah you'd be really You Dig Dug
into the bone now which is scratching
for this 30 40 50 years
so this single one single phenomenon the
question yeah is the sense of self
exactly yeah that's what it is
see because of that sense of self
that that
you perpetuate as we said that the truth
is like despite all the signs and
features of your mind you're still like
yeah this is I am this this is mine yeah
that's why mine has the unchecked
playing over you
and anything that might change is you'll
be under because you took it to your
ownership so by removal to seeing the
independence of the Mind the Anita the
duka of it the all these characteristics
uh you will stop maintaining this idea
that it's yours that you are it
um and uh and that's it that is
unburdening you actually from
the changes in that mind whichever way
it goes doesn't matter
but for as long as there is that
identity whichever it goes the burden
will be on you that's why that
the precept The Virtue guiding the sense
that needs to be taken as a behavior
regardless of the State of Mind
regardless of what intentions you have
and what you're inclined to do or not no
this will not be done so you find a
common sort of principle they will now
unite your behavior regardless of the
mood yeah so you cannot act your way out of a
yeah so you cannot act your way out of a
certain mood because it is moods that
determines the action yeah so it's a
perversion and the order and then seeing
that might also prevent unnecessary
action and just endure the mind as mines
yeah and then uninclined see
that's kind of the whole point
again we say so many times how can you
practice gliddening of the Mind
experiencing the mind it's found in the
mind calming the mind if you don't even
see the mind
and if you see the money correctly you
would at least be a short buyer
thus when I saw the one that doesn't
happen starting so it's one or higher
there's an open Sati he can by that time
because he already has discerned his
mind sufficiently as this an independent
phenomena that he's Within
and then he can okay now let me just
experience the Mind regardless of the
specific state that mind is let me read in let me
state that mind is let me read in let me
read out while experiencing in mind
while re-familiarizing myself with the
phenomenon of enduring mind that I am
subjected to
and let me let me glad in that mine
maybe make it lighter
let me unincline it from these
directions of sensuality
in other words you're so skilled now to
recognize these precursors to
obvious kind of perceptions you can
attend to You're So skilled in
recognizing these behaviors of a king
given before King he knows what he's
about to do you already see because you
love watched it and learned so closely
not through examination with your eyes
but through what in the damn eye see on
the level of the mind and then yeah
um you could then basically your mind
wants to go here wants to go there but
you are the one who sets up the
direction and sends the mind in the
right direction in the right way that's
like The Taming of the elephant so that
you can train the elephant so he
actually starts listening
so your chapter basically starts
listening to what you're well restrained
fatally understood Mana tells it to do
so it should intellect what's your
recognition what your what your kind of
wisdom tells it to do the mind that goes
their way
that's which results in fortifying the
four foundations of that right memory
mindfulness we're talking about gladdening the mind
we're talking about gladdening the mind
and so on so liberating the Mind
liberating the mind yeah yeah yeah so
you can now as I said by being familiar
with that phenomena of enduring mind
Discerning the slightest signs and
features of it you don't need big coarse
moods to see where the mind is
the slightest signs and features the
slightest movements so to speak of
neutral undefined kind it's enough for
you to see the mind to see the state of
the mind even before the minds are very
even before it has assumed the direction
and so on
and that's pretty much by that point
you'll be abandoning any five lower
factors because that level of being the level of
because that level of being the level of
requirement of Mind leaning is gone now
because you got so used to seeing it
even before as I said I mean King
doesn't move the little finger you
already know
where this would go so you either allow
it or not so all these little signs and
features and tokens all these
inclinations all these nimeters all
these four tellers
of mine is about to you know go and
engage mentally lean towards lust and
then you have to endure the pain of it
now you've seen that now I've seen that
even before the Mind recognized those
things were there
and then you you turn it away you send
it the other way
and that's exactly the practice of oh
can the other reason last arise in me
in a mind and a skillful man could
recognize those little telltales
oh am I welcoming am I with this
unsuitable kind so basically defining
the principle of skillful skillful and
skillful and unskillful
hasn't has understood that as a
principle but hasn't understood the
and kind of satellite implications of it
because if he did he would abandon even
that and then he'd be an anagram or
another
but when you say you recognize before
the mind even sees what recognizes
like how is that possible
how can you recognize before it's um
present so they say or is it present for
you before it's present for the mind or
it's present for both but you see the
mind doesn't because you see clearly hmm
it's possible because you're not the
Mind mind is a separate thing and during
the winter sense itself now obviously if
you're to the point of seeing the Mind
correctly Independence that you that we
talk about that sense of self is your
not self but that creature is still
there as the suit is referred to
that pugala that individual is still
there and he is the one who guards the
mind because that's Pleasant Here and
Now and he's the one who has liberated the
and he's the one who has liberated the
mind so with the Aggregates break apart
of that individual there will be no more
rebirth there will be no more taking up
things because the mind is turned away
from all of it because you made it to
turn away
you liberated it that's why you know
that it's liberated because you did it
it didn't happen to you and that's what
the city says
he knows oh it's liberated
so there is no doubt there anymore the
mind is turned away gone
through first taming it then training it
then directing it and gladdening it then
liberating it
and he has no desire to return anymore
because the only reason he kept
returning is because
he wanted to be free from suffering
which was in returning was what was
making it suffer so the vicious circle